Guide to the Samuel Zagat Drawings and Photographs TAM.623
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Samuel Zagat Drawings and Photographs
1912-1962
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Zagat, Samuel, 1890-1964
Zagat, Ida R.
TAM.623
11.25 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 6 oversize flat boxes, and 4 card file boxes.
Samuel Zagat was a Lithuanian-Jewish artist best known for his work as a cartoonist, first for his popular comic strip Gimpel Beinish" and later for his political cartoons. This collection documents Zagat's career as a cartoonist and more generally illustrates the efforts of an American cartoonist working in Yiddish. Materials include photographs, original drawings, negatives, contact prints, and newspaper clippings. Major subjects include labor relations, anti-Semitism, Cold War diplomacy, Israel and the Middle East, and humorous aspects of daily Jewish life.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The collection was donated by Ida R. Zagat in 1974. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1974.008, 1974.009, and 1974.010.
Existence and Location of Copies
Reference photocopies of the materials in portfolios 1-7 and 9-10 of the Original Drawing Portfolios are available. These may aid researchers in browsing the collection. The copies are in binders located in boxes 14-15 of the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series:
Missing Title
Original Drawing Portfolios
Cartoons by Publication
Cartoons by Year
Lower East Side Photographs
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Zagat (1890-1964), a Lithuanian-Jewish artist and cartoonist who emigrated to New York City as a child. Zagat is best known for his comic strip "Gimpl Beinish", published in the Yiddish-language newspaper "Warheit" from 1912 to 1919, and later for his political cartoons published in the "Jewish Daily Forward" from 1919 until his death in 1964. "The Forward", where Zagat also headed the art department and supervised the newspaper's weekly rotogravure feature, also published his drawings of street life, court sessions, and theater. His cartoons and drawings also appeared in numerous other publications, including the "New Masses", "Jewish Morning Journal", and "The Hat Worker", a publication of the Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers Union.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents Samuel Zagat's career as a cartoonist and more generally illustrates the efforts of an American cartoonist working in Yiddish. The collection contains photographs, original drawings, negatives (presumably taken from the screen of a microfilm reader), contact prints of negatives, newspaper clippings, and photocopies of Zagat's cartoons from the 1910s through the 1960s. The majority of the materials are from the 1940s and 1950s. Major subjects include labor relations, anti-Semitism, Cold War diplomacy, Israel and the Middle East, and humorous aspects of daily Jewish life. A substantial portion of Zagat's cartoons contain Yiddish captions; the majority of materials in this collection have supplied English translations.
Labor laws and legislation -- United States.; Fasts and feasts |x Judaism |v Pictorial works.; Drawings (visual works); Negatives (photographic); Cold War in mass media.; Jewish history, life, and culture.; Photographs.; Political cartoons.; Sukkot |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) |v Pictorial works.; Political cartoons -- United States.; Rosh ha-Shanah |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Zagat, Ida R.
- Original Drawing Portfolios
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into ten portfolios based on the cartoons' thematic subjects.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series consists of ten portfolios of original drawings by Samuel Zagat. The drawings were grouped into portfolios concerning specific subjects, including economics, World War II, anti-Semitism, Cold War diplomacy, daily Jewish life, Israel and the Middle East, and American domestic and foreign policy. Reference photocopies of the drawings from portfolios 1-7 and 9-10 are available, and may aid researchers in browsing the collection.
  - Portfolio 1: Capital and Labor, 1933-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Portfolio 1: Labor, Illustrations for book published by Hatters Union, undated (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Portfolio 2: United States Political Cartoons, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-17)
  - Portfolio 3: International Politics, 1955-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Portfolio 4: Israel, Near East, Anti-Semitism, 1955-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
  - Portfolio 5: Jewish Humor, 1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-14, Box 4, Folder 1-15)
  - Portfolio 6: USSR, 1955-1971, undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 1, Box 5, Folder 1-9)
  - Portfolio 7: Nazis, undated (Box 6, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001)
  - Portfolio 8: The Hat Worker, 1920-1961 (Box 7, Folder 1-24)
  - Portfolio 9: USA Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 2-3, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 1)
  - Portfolio 10: Works Exhibited March 7, 1974, undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 1, Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Reference Photocopies: Portfolios 1-4 and Index, 1933-1959 (Box 14)
  - Reference Photocopies: Portfolios 5-7, 9-10, 1920-1971 (Box 15)
- Cartoons by Publication
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title, thereunder chronologically.
  This series consists of prints and negatives of Samuel Zagat's comic strips and political cartoons. Included are individual cartoons and several of Zagat's long-running comic strips, like Gimpl Beinish. Topics include labor relations, anti-Semitism, Cold War diplomacy, and humorous aspects of daily Jewish life.
  - Forward, 1916-1961 (Box 10, Item 1-266)
  - The Hat Worker, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - The Hat Worker, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - The Hat Worker, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - The Hat Worker, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - The Hat Worker, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - The Hat Worker, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - The Hat Worker, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - The Hat Worker, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - The Hat Worker, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - The Hat Worker, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - The Hat Worker, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - The Hat Worker, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - The Hat Worker, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - The Hat Worker, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - The Hat Worker, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - The Hat Worker, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - The Hat Worker, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - The Hat Worker, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - The Hat Worker, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - The Hat Worker, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - The Hat Worker, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - The Hat Worker, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - The Hat Worker, undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, May 1919-Jun 1919 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Jul 1919 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Aug 1919 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Sep 1919 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Oct 1919 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Nov 1919-Dec 1919 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Jan 1920-Feb 1920 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Mar 1920-May 1920 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Jun 1920-Aug 1920 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, Sep 1920-Dec 1920 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Jewish Morning Journal: Prints, 1943-1950 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Jewish Morning Journal: Negatives, 1919-1959 (Box 10, Item 382-411, Box 11, Item 1-81)
  - New Masses, 1941-1955 (Box 11, Item 82-88)
  - Warheit: General, Jul 1915-Dec 1915 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Warheit: General, Jan 1919 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Warheit: General, Feb 1919 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Warheit: Named series: Abie's Moving Pictures, Dec 1912-Apr 1913 (Box 11, Item 89-123)
  - Warheit: Named series: Berl Bedroom the Boarder, Nov 1912-Mar 1914 (Box 11, Item 124-148)
  - Warheit: Named series: Der Boss, Dec 31, 1912-Jan 20, 1913 (Box 11, Item 149)
  - Warheit: Named series: Enough to Give You a Fit, Sep 1913-Oct 1913 (Box 11, Item 150-151)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jan 1915 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Feb 1915 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Mar 1915 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Apr 1915 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jan 1916-Apr 1916 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, May 1916 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jun 1916 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jul 1916-Sep 1916 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Oct 1916 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Nov 1916 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Dec 1916 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jan 1917-Mar 1917 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Apr 1917 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, May 1, 1917-May 15, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, May 16, 1917-May 31, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jun 1, 1917-Jun 14, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jun 1, 1917-Jun 30, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jul 1, 1917-Jul 10, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jul 11, 1917-Jul 18, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Dec 2, 1917-Dec 26, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Dec 27, 1917-Dec 31, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jan 1918-Apr 1918 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, May 1918 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Jun 1918-Aug 1918 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Sep 1918-Oct 1918 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Oct 1918-Nov 1918 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints, Dec 1918 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints (1 of 2), Jan 1919-Feb 1919 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Prints (2 of 2), Jan 1919-Feb 1919 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Warheit: Named series: Gimpl Beinish: Negatives, 1912-1919 (Box 11, Item 152-402, Box 12, Item 1-207)
  - Warheit: Named series: Khane Pesl, The Second, 1912-1913 (Box 12, Item 208-259, Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Warheit: Named series: Mrs. Yederman, Nov 1914-Dec 1914 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Warheit: Named series: Sunday is a Day of Rest, Sep 7, 1913-Oct 19, 1913 (Box 12, Item 260-264)
  - Warheit: Named series: Suzy Knaknisl, 1916 (Box 12, Item 265-273, Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Warheit: Named series: Two Views of Life, Jun 1913-Aug 1913 (Box 12, Item 274-290)
  - Warheit: Named series: Yiddish Theatre, 1913 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Warheit: Short-lived cartoons, Mar 30, 1912-Feb 13, 1919 (Box 13, Item 1-111, Box 12, Item 291-394)
- Cartoons by Year
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  This series consists of prints of Samuel Zagat's political cartoons that appeared in a variety of unidentifiable publications. Topics include economics, labor relations, anti-Semitism, Cold War diplomacy, and humorous aspects of daily Jewish life.
  - 1912 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1913 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1916 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Jan 1917-Mar 1917 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Apr 1917 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - May 1917-Dec 1917 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - 1918 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - circa 1935 (Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Negatives, Apr 27, 1917-Dec 1959 (Box 13, Item 112-180)
- Lower East Side Photographs
  This series consists of negatives and 56 8 x 10 black-and-white photographs by Zagat on New York City's Lower East Side in 1931 prior to the Jewish high holidays of Rosh Hashanah and Sukkot. The photographs include images of people on a pier (probably near the East River), many of them holding what are probably prayer books and presumably waiting to perform the Tashlikh, a Rosh Hashanah custom in which celebrants gather by a body of flowing water and turn their pockets out, symbolically casting off their sins. Other photographs depict shoppers purchasing the ritual Sukkot items lulav and esrog (a palm front bound together with willow branches and a citrus fruit, respectively) from street vendors, as well as merchants selling skullcaps, shoes, and dishes at outdoor stands. Most locations are not identified. Some items in this series were published in the Jewish Daily Forward.
  - Photographs shot by Samuel Zagat on New York City's Lower East Side (18 prints), 1931 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Photographs shot by Samuel Zagat on New York City's Lower East Side (12 prints), 1931 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Photographs shot by Samuel Zagat on New York City's Lower East Side (12 prints), 1931 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Photographs shot by Samuel Zagat on New York City's Lower East Side (14 prints), 1931 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Negatives from Jewish Life on New York's Lower East Side, circa 1931 (Box 10, Item 267-381)